Guide to the Caryl Phillips Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Caryl Phillips papers
1940-2015
1979-2015
GEN MSS 793
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
94.51
(114 boxes) + 2 rolls
The Caryl Phillips Papers consists of correspondence, writings, research files, business papers, computer disks, audio recordings and printed material created and accumulated by Caryl Phillips from circa 1979 until 2006, including some research material with earlier dates. Writings include drafts (autograph manuscripts, typescripts, printouts, and computer files) and other material related to all of his major works during this time period, including the plays Strange Fruit (1981), Where There is Darkness (1982), and The Shelter (1984), and the novels The Final Passage (1985), A State of Independence (1986), Higher Ground (1989), Cambridge (1991), Crossing the River (1993), The Nature of Blood (1997), A Distant Shore (2003), and Dancing in the Dark (2005). Writings also include drafts and other material related to articles, lectures, and reviews. Correspondence is chiefly professional in nature, and relates to writings, publishing, and other professional activities.
Phillips, Caryl
Existence and Location of Copies
Copies of electronic files are available through Access Services.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2000-2006.
February 2016 Acquisiton: purchased from Caryl Phillips on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 35-36 and 75-77: Restricted until 2050. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Boxes 37, 74, and 116 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 4, 5, 7, 12, 15-20, 72 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Arrangement
Organized into three groupings: February 2000 Acquisition, September 2006 Acquisition, and February 2016 Acquisition.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time. Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with or relates to material found in other acquisitions (e.g. correspondence and writings can be found in both groupings). In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers should consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
Scope and Contents
The Caryl Phillips Papers consists of correspondence, writings, research files, business papers, computer disks, audio recordings, and printed material created and accumulated by Caryl Phillips from circa 1979 until 2006. Writings include drafts (autograph manuscripts, typescripts, printouts, and computer files) and other material related to all of his major works during this time period, including the plays Strange Fruit (1981), Where There is Darkness (1982), The Shelter (1984), and the novels The Final Passage (1985), A State of Independence (1986), Higher Ground (1989), Cambridge (1991), Crossing the River (1993), The Nature of Blood (1997), A Distant Shore (2003), and Dancing in the Dark (2005). Writings also include drafts and other material related to articles, lectures, and reviews. Correspondence is chiefly professional in nature, and relates to writings, publishing, and other professional activities.
Caryl Phillips (1958-)
Caryl Phillips, born in 1958 in St. Kitts, is a British playwright, screenwriter, and novelist. He is a Professor of English at Yale University.
Authors, English -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, English -- 21st century -- Archives; Commonwealth literature (English); Dramatists; Novelists; Screenwriters; West Indian literature (English); Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Electronic documents; Audiotapes; Dramatists, English; Novelists, English; Screenwriters; Phillips, Caryl
- February 2000 Acquisition, 1979-1997; 30.59; (37 boxes) + 2 rolls
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 35-36: Restricted until 2050. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  Box 37: (computer disks): Original computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files are available through Access Services.
  Audio cassettes in boxes 4, 5, 7, 12, 15-20: Use of original audio cassettes is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Arrangement
  Organized under five headings: Published Books by Phillips, Stage, Film and Radio Projects, Other Writings by Phillips, Reviews and Press Reports on Phillips' Work, and Correspondence and Business Records.
  General note
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 15
  Scope and Contents
  The February 2000 Acquisition consists of writings, correspondence, and business records dating from 1979 to 1997. Material related to many, though not all, of Phillips' early writings can be found in this acquisition, including later drafts of Strange Fruit (1981), and drafts of Cambridge (1991), Crossing the River (1993), The Nature of Blood (1997). Correspondence is chiefly with publishers. Other material includes reviews and clippings related to Phillips' life and work.
  - Published Books by Phillips
    Files are grouped together according to title but are not arranged in any particular order.
    - Crossing the River
      - Research material; Liberia, [1992]; 9 (Box 1)
      - Research material; W.W.2, GI's, England, [1992-1995]; 16 (Box 1)
      - Research material; W.W.2, GI's, England, [1992-1995]; 15 (Box 2)
      - Research material; U.S., Wild West, [1990-1995]; 9; Includes 9 computer disks (Box 2)
        Existence and Location of Copies
        Available through Access Services:
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #1; 1-28.
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #2; Section 4: 1-10, Section 5: 1-2.
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #3; Section 2 continued: 30-to the end, 47.
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #4; Section 2: 1-30.
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #5; 138-160, 140-162.
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #6; 108-139.
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #7; 101-107.
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #8; 57-70.
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #9; 29-55.
        Original computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files are available through Access Services.
      - Research material; U.S., Wild West, [1990-1995]; 9 (Box 3)
      - Early writings, notes and drafts, [1990-1995]; 9 (Box 3)
      - Corrected proofs; audio cassette, 1992-1995; 8 (Box 4)
        Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Autograph manuscript notes, and typescript drafts of the various parts of the novel; audio cassette, [1990-1995]; 11 (Box 5)
      - Drafts, photocopy of the typescript layout for book, [1992-1995]; 12; Includes 4 computer disks (Box 5)
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #10; Prologue, Epilogue, Title, Acknowledgements, Part 1 (original).
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #11; Prologue, Epilogue, Title, Acknowledgements, Part 1 (duplicate).
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #12; Parts II, III, IV (duplicate).
        Uncat MSS 15 Disk #13; Parts II, III, IV (original).
    - The Nature of Blood
      - Notes and planning plus revisions, 1994-1996; 14 (Box 6)
      - Research material, 1994-1997; 7 (Box 6)
      - Research material; audio cassettes, 1994-1997; 16 (Box 7)
      - Original writings, 1995-1996; 10; Includes 1 computer disk (Box 8)
        Available through Access Services: Uncat MSS 15 Disk #14; Version of novel from ?Carde 95/Thailand 96.
      - Proofs, 1996-1997; 7; Includes 1 computer disk (Box 8)
        Available through Access Services: Uncat MSS 15 Disk #15; Bangkok 31/1/96.
      - Full draft manuscripts, 1996-1997; 12 (Box 9)
    - Cambridge
      - Research material, [1985-1988]; 9 (Box 9)
      - Notes and typescripts, 1986-1989; 19 (Box 10)
      - Completed drafts and proofs, 1990; 7 (Box 10)
    - The Final Passage, Autograph manuscript, edited drafts, proofs, and related correspondence, 1995; 16 (Box 11)
    - A State of Independence, Notes, out-takes, final drafts, editors notes, proofs and correspondence, 1985; 6 (Box 11)
    - The European Tribe, drafts, notes, audio cassette and related correspondence, 1982-1986, undated; 15 (Box 12)
    - Higher Ground, notes, drafts, proofs and manuscript, 1989; 17 (Box 13)
  - Stage, Film and Radio Projects
    Files are grouped together according to title, but are not arranged in any particular order.
    - Point of Departure, notes, correspondence, two drafts, mixed typescripts and photo-typescript, 1983; 2 (Box 13)
    - The Shelter, three rehearsal scripts, 1983 (Box 13)
    - The Record, production and shooting schedule with two mixed photo-typescripts, 1983; 2 (Box 13)
    - The Promised Land, typescript, corrected, 1982 (Box 13)
    - Celebration, Original typescript and photo-typescript, 1979 (Box 14)
    - Playing Away, Shooting script and draft typescripts, 1984-1986; 7 (Box 14)
    - Pioneers, typescripts, 1985 (Box 14)
    - Strike, draft, typescript and manuscript, research material and final typescript, 1984-1988; 5 (Box 14)
    - Curtis Mayfield, Research material, interview transcripts, notes and script, 1995; 2 (Box 14)
    - Lost in Music, Shooting schedule and typescripts, [1985] (Box 14)
    - Where There is Darkness, three drafts with holograph revisions, 1981; 3 (Box 14)
    - Hotel Cristobel, notes, typescripts, drafts and promotional material, 1985-1994; 15; Includes 2 computer disks (Box 15)
      Uncat MSS 15 Disk #16; Original Nov. 1990.
      Uncat MSS 15 Disk #17; Duplicate Back up copy.
    - Hotel Cristobel, original art work for the promotional poster, 1996 (Box 78 ROLL)
    - Volunteering, research files and typescript, 1991; 2 (Box 15)
    - The Prince of Africa, correspondence, typescripts and dialogue transcript, 1984-1986; 2 (Box 15)
    - The Hope and the Glory, shooting script, 1982 (Box 15)
    - Crossing the River (Radio adaptation), notes, drafts, typescripts and audio cassette, 1985 (Box 15)
    - Children of the City, episode one and three typescripts, [1985]; 2 (Box 15)
    - Strange Fruit, two typescript drafts with related material, [1980-1984]; 2 (Box 16)
    - Uptown Top Ranking, typescript, undated (Box 16)
    - The Wasted Years, typescript with manuscript revisions, correspondence and audio cassette, 1984 (Box 16)
    - James Baldwin, interview and revised typescripts with research material and audio cassettes, 1985; 3 (Box 16)
    - The Ebony Imposter, revised working typescript, final typescript, promotional and contractual materials, 1985; 6 (Box 16)
    - Writing Fiction, drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript, final production script; audio cassette, 1988; 4 (Box 16)
    - State of Independence, typescript (copy), 1987 (Box 16)
    - Spirit of America
      - Research audio cassettes, undated; (15 audiocassettes) (Box 17)
      - Research notes, [1989-1995]; 2 (Box 18)
    - Black Panthers, research material, 1986-1989 (Box 18)
    - All or Nothing At All, notes, drafts, typescript and manuscript, correspondence, promotional material; audio cassette, 1989; 13 (Box 18)
    - Blind Case, typescript with manuscript notes, undated (Box 18)
    - Black on Black, three typescript drafts, undated (Box 18)
    - Settling Down, typescript, with correspondence, 1981 (Box 18)
    - Bunny's Carnival, files of revisions, typescripts with revisions and notebook, 1990; 4 (Box 18)
    - St. Kitts. Independence, Pride of Place. Scripts with related material; audio cassette, 1983 (Box 19)
    - Birmingham & Welcome to Birmingham, typescripts with related material, [1985] (Box 19)
    - Brother, first draft, manuscript and typescripts, revised, 1988; 8 (Box 19)
    - Somewhere in England (screenplay), draft, 1997; 2 (Box 19)
    - Extravagant Strangers
      - Complete working file from drafts to final typescript layout [folders 1-7], 1995-1997; 7 (Box 19)
      - Complete working file from drafts to final typescript layout [folders 8-14], 1995-1997; 7 (Box 20)
    - Celebration, stories and early writings, 1979-1980; 2 (Box 20)
    - Speak, writings for the BBC; audio cassette, 1981-1982 (Box 20)
  - Other Writings by Phillips
    - Early works, edited manuscript, typescripts, [1980-1995]; 2 (Box 20)
    - Magazine articles, 1982-1983 (Box 20)
    - Theatre reviews, manuscript and typescript, 1986 (Box 20)
    - Reviews and manuscript notes, 1987 (Box 20)
    - Various writings, drafts and related printed material, 1988-1996; 21 (Box 21)
    - Magazine, newspaper and typescript articles, 1997; 7 (Box 22)
    - Bomb. Magazine for the Arts
    - New York Times, Arts and Leisure Section
    - The Guardian Weekend
  - Reviews and Press Reports on Phillips' Work
    - Reviews and Press, 1985-1993; 12 (Box 22)
    - Reviews and Press, 1994-1997; 13 (Box 23)
    - Biographical article, 1987 (Box 24)
    - Interview and articles, 1990 (Box 24)
    - Interviews, articles and literary journals, 1991-1994; 11 (Box 24)
    - Articles and correspondence, 1995; 2 (Box 24)
    - Articles, 1996-1997 (Box 24)
  - Correspondence and Business Records
    Files are grouped together according to type of material but are not arranged in any particular order.
    - Knopf. Correspondence, contracts, business papers, photographs, book jacket covers and promotional material, 1991-1998; 3 (Box 25)
    - Penguin/Viking. Correspondence, catalogue, book covers and financial arrangements, 1989-1993 (Box 25)
    - Faber and Faber. Correspondence, contracts, book covers and business papers, 1988-1993; 5 (Box 25)
    - Curtis Brown. Correspondence and business papers, 1990-1993 (Box 25)
    - Wylie Aitken and Stone. Correspondence and business papers, 1987-1992 (Box 25)
    - Rogers Coleridge and White, 1980-1990 (Box 25)
    - Vintage. Cover proofs, related correspondence and promotional material, 1992-1995 (Box 25)
    - Aitken and Stone, 1988-1996 (Box 25)
    - Farrar Straus Giroux. Catalogues, correspondence and book covers, 1986-1988 (Box 25)
    - Bloomsbury. Graphic items, covers, reviews and correspondence, 1993; 2 (Box 25)
    - Picador. Original art work for covers, proofs of book covers, correspondence., 1993 (Box 25)
    - Posters promoting Phillips' books from various publishing houses, 1990-1997 (Box 79 ROLL)
    - Judy Daish Associates Ltd., 1980-1997; 5 (Box 26)
    - Foreign Language Publications, correspondence, catalogues, and book covers, 1980-1997 (Box 26)
    - Publishing contracts, 1990-1994 (Box 26)
    - Publishing financial statements, 1987-1993 (Box 26)
    - General, Personal and Business Correspondence
      - Faxes, e-mail, postcards, letters, manuscript, typescript, and printouts [folders 1-6], 1985-1991; 6 (Box 26)
      - Faxes, e-mail, postcards, letters, manuscript, typescript, and printouts [folders 7-24], 1992-1994; 18 (Box 27)
      - Faxes, e-mail, postcards, letters, manuscript, typescript, and printouts [folders 25-32], 1995-1998; 8 (Box 28)
      - Faxes, e-mail, postcards, letters, manuscript, typescript, and printouts [folders 33-35], 1995-1998; 3 (Box 29)
    - General correspondence from Phillips' file folders, 1990-1999; 20 (Box 29)
      Arranged alphabetically.
    - Postcards, 1990-1999; 4 (Box 30)
      Greeting, birthday, announcements and general correspondence on postcards.
    - Visits, 1988-1994; 10 (Box 30)
      Correspondence, programmes and related information on symposiums, lectures and book festivals attended by Phillips.
    - Visits (continued), 1995-1997; 3 (Box 31)
  - Oversize Material
    - Bomb. Magazine for the Art, 1992-1994, 1997 (Box 32)
    - The Guardian Weekend, 1997 June 21 (Box 33)
    - The New York Times, Arts and Leisure Section, 1997 September 7 (Box 33)
    - Promotional material from Knopf and Vintage book publishers, 1990-1994 (Box 34)
      Includes material related to Phillips' appearances in England and Indonesia.
  - Restricted Papers
    Boxes 35-36: Restricted until 2050. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
    - Correspondence (Box 35)
    - Correspondence (Box 36)
  - Computer media
    Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Formatted CAZ "PRIVATE." 1-28, 2000-genm-0222-c-0001; 1 (Box 37)
    - section 3: 1-4 Format Section 4 1-10 section 5:- 1-2, 2000-genm-0222-c-0002; 1 (Box 37)
    - Format section 2 continued 30 -- To The End 47, 2000-genm-0222-c-0003; 1 (Box 37)
    - Format section 2 1-30, 2000-genm-0222-c-0004; 1 (Box 37)
    - Formatted 1-160 140-162 Repaginated 50, 2000-genm-0222-c-0005; 1 (Box 37)
    - Format 108-139 Repag 50, 2000-genm-0222-c-0006; 1 (Box 37)
    - Formatted 101-107 Repag 50, 2000-genm-0222-c-0007; 1 (Box 37)
    - Format 57-70 repagination, 2000-genm-0222-c-0008; 1 (Box 37)
    - Format 29-55 repagination, 2000-genm-0222-c-0009; 1 (Box 37)
    - original Prologue Epilogue Title/acknowledgements Part I Caz Phillips - Novel, 2000-genm-0222-c-0010; 1 (Box 37)
    - duplicate Prologue Epilogue Title/ack. Part I C.P- Novel, 2000-genm-0222-c-0011; 1 (Box 37)
    - duplicate Parts II, III, IV CP - Novel, 2000-genm-0222-c-0012; 1 (Box 37)
    - original Parts II, III, IV Caz Phillips- Novel, 2000-genm-0222-c-0013; 1 (Box 37)
    - BOOK (version of novel from Carde 95 / Thailand 96) (The Nature of Blood), 2000-genm-0222-c-0014; 1 (Box 37)
    - BOOK Bangkok 31/1/96, 2000-genm-0222-c-0015; 1 (Box 37)
    - Caz Phillips HOTEL CRISTOBEL Original VOLUNTEERING November 1990 WordPerfect 5.0, 2000-genm-0222-c-0016; 1 (Box 37)
    - Caz Phillips HOTEL CRISTOBEL Duplicate (Backup Copy) November 1990 WordPerfect 5.0, 2000-genm-0222-c-0017; 1 (Box 37)
- September 2006 Acquisition, 1940-2006; 38; (40 boxes)
  Organized under four headings: Correspondence, Writings, Visits, and Audio Recordings.
  Boxes 75-77: Restricted until 2050. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  Box 72 (audio tapes): Use of original audio tapes is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 895
  The September 2006 Acquisition consists of writings, research files, correspondence, business records, and audio recordings dating from 1940 to 2006, with the bulk of material dating from 1979 to 2006. Writings include early drafts of Strange Fruit (1981) and material for Celebration (1980) as well as later writings such as The Atlantic Sound (2000), Dancing in the Dark (2005), and the screen adaptation of Mystic Masseur (2001). Correspondence is chiefly with publishers or relates to lectures and professional travel. Other material includes reviews and clippings related to Phillips' life and work, and audio recordings relating to Phillips' research and work.
  - Correspondence
    Organized by type of correspondence, and further arranged chronologically.
    - General correspondence, 1998 (Box 38)
    - General correspondence, 1998-2000 (Box 38)
    - General correspondence, 1999; 2 (Box 38)
    - General correspondence, 2000; 2 (Box 38)
    - General correspondence, 2001; 3 (Box 38)
    - General correspondence, 2002 (Box 38)
    - General correspondence, 2003; 2 (Box 38)
    - General correspondence, 2004; 3 (Box 38)
    - General correspondence, 2005; 2 (Box 38)
    - Agents and publishers, 1998-2000; 3 (Box 39)
    - Agents and publishers, 2000-2001; 2 (Box 39)
    - Agents and publishers, 2001; 2 (Box 39)
    - Agents, 2002 (Box 39)
    - Agents, 2003; 2 (Box 39)
    - Agents, 2004; 2 (Box 39)
    - Agents, 2005 (Box 39)
  - Writings
    Organized under two headings: Novels, Playscripts and Screenplays, and Reviews and Interviews.
    - Novels, Playscripts, and Screenplays
      Arranged alphabetically by title.
      - The Atlantic Sound
        - Drafts and correspondence, 1996-2000; 6 (Box 39)
        - Research, 1976-1989; 2 (Box 40)
        - Dimona research, 1998 (Box 40)
        - Elmina Castle, manuscript, 1996-1997 (Box 40)
        - Charleston, undated (Box 40)
        - Ghana, manuscript, undated (Box 40)
        - Epilogue Exodus, undated (Box 40)
        - Page proofs, 2000; 2 (Box 40)
        - Homeward bound, corrected drafts, undated; 2 (Box 40)
        - Liverpool text, corrected drafts, undated; 2 (Box 40)
        - Proofs, 2000 January; 2 (Box 40)
        - First draft, typescript, undated (Box 40)
        - Drafts, typescript, undated (Box 40)
        - Second draft, typescript, undated (Box 40)
        - Third draft, typescript, undated (Box 40)
        - American proofs and corrections, 2000; 2 (Box 41)
        - Research, 1940-1998; 3 (Box 41)
        - Notes, 1987-1996 (Box 41)
        - Draft, printout, corrected, 1999 March 15 (Box 41)
        - Draft, printout, corrected, [1999] (Box 41)
        - Page proofs, 2000; 2 (Box 41)
        - Page proofs, corrections, 2000; 2 (Box 41)
        - Notes for final draft, undated; 1 folder and 3 computer disks. (Box 41)
          Uncat MSS 895 Disk #1; The Atlantic Sound.
          Uncat MSS 895 Disk #2; Bert Notes 2, 2004 August 13.
          Uncat MSS 895 Disk #17; The Atlantic Sound.
        - Dimona research, 1999 (Box 41)
        - Marked-up draft, 1999; 2 (Box 41)
        - First draft, undated (Box 41)
        - Atlantic Crossing, prologue, 1997; 2 (Box 41)
        - Contacts, 1997-1998 (Box 41)
        - General notes, 1985-1997 (Box 41)
        - Draft, undated (Box 41)
        - Leaving home, printout, corrected, undated; 1 folder and 1 computer disk. (Box 42)
          Available through Access Services: Uncat MSS 895 Disk #5; Leaving Home, Charleston, Liverpool, recent notes for Liverpool.
        - Charleston research, 1992-1999 (Box 42)
        - Ghana research, 1996-1997 (Box 42)
        - Final draft, printout, 1999 August; 2 (Box 42)
        - Draft, printout, corrected, 1999 August; 2 (Box 42)
        - Homeward Bound, draft, 1999, undated; 1 folder and 1 computer disk. (Box 42)
          Available through Access Services: Uncat MSS 895 Disk #4; Homeward Bound, Home, Prologue, (Dimona Notes), Exodus.
        - Part III. Home, draft, printout, corrected, 1999, undated (Box 42)
        - Exodus draft, printout, corrected, undated; 1 folder and 1 computer disk. (Box 42)
          Available through Access Services: Uncat MSS 895 Disk #3; Homeward Bound 1999 August 7.
        - General Ghana notes, 1997 (Box 42)
        - Elmina, 1996-1999; 4 (Box 42)
        - Ghana Research, undated (Box 42)
        - Liverpool research, 1997-1998, undated; 2 (Box 42)
      - Celebration: a Collection of Short Stories, draft, autograph manuscript and typescript, corrected, 1979 (Box 43)
      - Celebration (television script), working draft, autograph manuscript, accompanied by clean typescript, 1979 (Box 43)
      - Dancing in the Dark
        - Computer disks, 2004; (4 computer disks)
          Uncat MSS 895 Disk #6; CP's copy Dancing in the Dark 2004 October 27.
          Uncat MSS 895 Disk #7; Bert: Part 1, CP's copy 2004 August 13.
          Uncat MSS 895 Disk #8; Bert II and Bert inserts, 2004 September 24.
          Uncat MSS 895 Disk #9; Bert 3 CP and Bert notes.
        - Drafts and related papers, 2004-2005; 18 (Box 43)
        - Drafts and related papers, 2004-2005; 16 (Box 44)
        - Part 1, drafts, autograph manuscript and printouts, 2004-2005; 12 (Box 45)
        - Part 2, draft, autograph manuscript and printouts, 2004-2005; 7 (Box 45)
        - Part 2, draft, autograph manuscript and printouts, 2004-2005; 16 (Box 46)
      - A Distant Shore